# Md Kamruzzaman (Methun)

mhmethun@gmail.com | (509) 336-9938 | Folsom, CA, USA | linkedin.com/in/mhmethun

### **Summary**

Ph.D.-trained researcher and software developer with 5+ years in applied machine learning, solving cross-domain problems including infectious disease, health anomaly detection, and drug discovery in science and technology. Expert in SFT, PEFT, and generative AI (VAE, WGAN, Diffusion), achieving 4x performance boosts and 95% efficiency gains using GPU clusters. Proficient in Python, C++, SQL, and MPI/OpenMP. Led 6-person teams, collaborated with Google, and seeks to advance ML innovation.

#### **Skills**

- · Machine Learning: SFT, PEFT, LoRA, VAE, WGAN, Diffusion Models, Ensemble Models, Hierarchical Models
- Data Science: ETL, Topological Data Analysis (TDA), Statistical Modeling, Graph-Based Algorithms
- Programming: Python, C++, CUDA, NodeJS, D3.js, Java, HTML/CSS, JavaScript, SQL
- Tools & Frameworks: Huggingface (dnaBERT2, EVO2, UTRLM, molgpt), PyTorch, TensorFlow, HPC Clusters (SLURM)
- · Additional: Privacy-Preserving ML, Data Visualization, Full-Stack Development, Git CI/CD, MLFlow, Docker
- Soft Skills: Collaborative, Team Player, Team Leadership, Bias for Action, Results-Driven

# **Professional Experience**

#### Postdoctoral Researcher (Applied Machine Learning), Sandia National Laboratories, Livermore, CA

May 2023-Present

- Advanced multilayered semi-realtime anomaly detection research on health sensor data (collected from Fitbit and Apple Watch) utilizing GPU and generative AI
  - Reduced cokurtosis tensor compute time by 5x on wearable health data (steps, heart-rate, sleep, etc) using CUDA on NVIDIA H100 GPU.
  - Improved anomaly detection accuracy for a 45,000-population (digital twins) by advancing generative AI models (VAE, WGAN, Diffusion), minimizing model uncertainty.
- Spearheaded molecular discovery research for a specific group of chemical compounds by fine-tuning LLM
  - Enhanced lab efficiency 95% by fine-tining Huggingface/molgpt with 1,000 candidate SMILEs strings, and generated 10k new molecules.
  - Discovered two industry-manufacturable candidate molecules utilizing an ensemble-based predictive and rule-based recommendation model from 10k new molecules.
  - Collaborated with cross-domain researchers to decipher actionable requirements and model explainability using SHAP.
- Led bioinformatics research on drug-repurposing and 5'UTR mRNA sequence classification
  - Tool development for FDA-approved drug candidates, improving drug repurposing strategies, using human-virus PPI, transcriptomic, and viral gene-drug interaction data.
  - Accelerated 5'UTR mRNA sequence classification by 4x, reducing training time, using SFT and PEFT with LoRA across 10M samples on a 10-node A100 GPU cluster.
- · Enhanced lattice QCD matrix element modeling accuracy at short distances and large momentum using generative AI techniques.
- · Mentor undergraduate and graduate interns and work closely to expedite the project delivery.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher (Applied Machine Learning), University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

Oct 2020-May 2023

- Led cross-domain research on machine learning applications in healthcare, implementing novel algorithms for detecting infection sources and risk assessment on IRB-approved HIPAA-compliant MRSA data.
  - Streamlined data preparation for model training by utilizing an ETL process to integrate daily data from two hospitals into a common data model.
  - Constructed a patient-provider temporal contact network, extracted latent features that improved model AUC by 15%.
  - Enhanced model accuracy by 7% on unbalanced EHR datasets by designing a novel hierarchical model algorithm.
- Strengthened healthcare application performance by implementing privacy-preserving ML solutions in collaboration with the Google research team.
- · Identified infection sources and missing cases using an agent-based model on an HPC cluster (MPICH) with SLURM, leveraging claim and prescription data.
- · Mentored undergraduate and graduate students and interns.

#### Research Assistant (Data Science), Washington State University, Pullman, WA

Aug 2015-Sep 2020

- Led research in algorithm development to extract actionable insights from complex and high-dimensional plant phenomics and hospital patient data.
  - Developed Hyppo-X, a CPP-based data analysis framework with integrated Topological Data Analysis (TDA) algorithms and interactive visualization tools, uncovering complex patterns in high-dimensional datasets.
  - Enabled breakthroughs in maize phenomics research by engineering a graph-based data analysis algorithm to extract scientific hypotheses from structural properties.
  - Delivered actionable insights for agricultural research by implementing statistical modeling for genotypic analysis under environmental stress.
  - Enhanced clinical insights by integrating NodeJS and D3.js for advanced data visualization of hospital patient trajectories.
  - Taught undergraduate students VeriLog, and software engineering.

#### Software Development Engineer, KBGroupUK & NRG, Dhaka, Bangladesh

May 2009-Jul 2015

- Built full-stack e-commerce websites using .NET, HTML/CSS, and JavaScript, increasing ticket sales by 13%.
- Led a 6-person team from 2013 to 2015, driving 5% year-over-year revenue growth.

#### **Internship Experience**

# Applied Scientist Intern, Amazon, Seattle, WA

Jun 2019-Sep 2019

· Optimized ML models (ARIMA, LSTM) for sales predictions, improving accuracy by 3% utilizing the Amazon SageMaker.

# Research Intern, Pacific Northwest National Laboratories, Richland, WA

Jul 2018-Aug 2018

• Engineered C++ solutions with SPDLOG, resolving Python asynchronous bottlenecks.

#### Education

# Ph.D., Computer Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA

Aug 2015-Aug 2020

**B.Sc., Computer Science and Engineering**, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

# Mar 2004-Mar 2009

#### **Additional Information**

- · Proficient in collaborating across interdisciplinary teams and presenting complex technical results to diverse stakeholders.
- Available for relocation and authorized to work in the United States without VISA sponsorship (GC holder).